{"tossups": [{"question": "A \u201crequiem\u201d titled for this battle states \u201cWhat like a bullet can undeceive,\u201d and was written by Herman Melville. Ambrose Bierce described \u201cWhat I Saw of [this battle]\u201d in an 1874 short story. At this battle, Lew Wallace, the author of<em> Ben-Hur</em>, led a division that marched along the Shunpike Road due to confusion in their battle orders. For ten points, name this Civil War battle fought in Tennessee near Pittsburg Landing.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Shiloh</b> (accept<b> Shiloh</b>: A Requiem; accept Battle of<b> Pittsburg Landing</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country lost international support after caning students who protested mandatory uniforms; that man, who spent 30 million dollars on a Napoleonic coronation, came to power in this country\u2019s Saint-Sylvestre coup, overthrowing David Dacko. Seleka rebels founded the Republic of Langone in this former French colony, which is currently ruled by Faustin-Archange Touadera. Jean-Bedel Bokassa once ruled, for ten points, what African country with capital at Bangui?", "answer": "<b> C</b>entral<b> A</b>frican<b> R</b>epublic", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman mentored Marie Zakrzewska, who helped grow her dispensary at Tompkins Square into an institution that merged with New York Presbyterian in 2013. After receiving backlash from the United States Sanitary Commission, this woman helped establish the Women\u2019s Central Relief Association during the Civil War. Charles Lee bowed to this woman in 1849 while granting her a degree earned after 150 students unanimously agreed to accept her admittance at Geneva College. For ten points, name this first woman to obtain an American medical degree.", "answer": "Elizabeth<b> Blackwell</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "French traders are considered the first Europeans to have explored this area\u2019s St. Francois and Boston Mountains. This region\u2019s White and Osage Rivers were dammed by the US Army Corps of Engineers in 1911 to create several new lakes, and its Mark Twain National Forest was restored by the Civilian Conservation Corps in the 1930s. The Whitewater scandal concerned land development in, for ten points, what mountainous plateau primarily located in northern Arkansas and southern Missouri?", "answer": "the<b> Ozark</b>s (accept<b> Ozark</b> Mountains; accept<b> Ozark</b> Plateau)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In this war, the USS<em> Essex</em> and USS<em> Essex Junior</em> were captured off the coast of Chile. One side in this war ambushed a convoy at Henderson Bay which led to the Second Battle of Sacket\u2019s Harbor. In an 1882 book, Theodore Roosevelt says the American navy gave the populace confidence in the face of an ineffectual army during this war. Fort Niagara was captured in, for ten points, what war in which Oliver Hazard Perry won the Battle of Lake Erie?", "answer": "War of<b> 1812</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Eugene Schuyler created a report of atrocities in this country. In this country, the Batak Massacre was caused by Bashi-Bazouks during the April Uprising. By the Treaty of San Stefano, this country was liberated from Ottoman Rule by Russia in 1878, but its northern neighbor gained Dobruja. William Gladstone denounced the \u201chorrors\u201d of this country in his Midlothian Campaign. Simeon II was the last Tsar of, for ten points, what Balkan nation north of Greece that is ruled from Sofia?", "answer": "<b> Bulgaria</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this African-American religious group that adopted traditions of the prophet Muhammad.", "answer": "<b> Nation of Islam</b> (accept<b> NOI</b>; do not accept or prompt on Islam alone)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This composer dramatized the destruction of Missolonghi during the Greek War of Indepenedence in his opera<em> The Siege of Corinth</em>. This composer repeated musical phrases in a namesake crescendo; that technique is employed in pieces like the overture to<em> The Thieving Magpie</em>. A galop known as \u201cThe March of the Swiss Soldiers\u201d concludes the overture to this man\u2019s final opera, which depicts a Swiss folk hero who shoots an apple off his son\u2019s head. For ten points, name this Italian composer of<em> William Tell</em>.", "answer": "Gioachino<b> Rossini</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The first of these works urges caution, stating that \u201cNothing valuable can be lost by taking time,\u201dbefore claiming that the \u201cbetter angels of our nature\u201d will once again stir the \u201cmystic chords of memory.\u201dOne of these speeches quotes Matthew 18:7, saying \u201cWoe unto the world because of offences,\u201d and calls slavery one of those offenses. The second of these speeches advises action \u201cWith malice toward none, with charity for all.\u201d For ten points, name these speeches delivered in 1861 and 1865 in Washington, DC.", "answer": "Abraham<b> Lincoln</b>\u2019s<b> Inaugural</b> Addresses (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cspeeches of Lincoln\u201d or \u201cinaugural speeches\u201d) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The generals Mundus and Mauricius died fighting this group at Salona. Boethius was executed for trying to kill a king of this group, who was served by Cassiodorus. At the Battle of Taginae, Narses killed Totila, a ruler of this group. The Lombards invaded the Byzantine Empire shortly after Justinian conquered this group. A ruler of these people, Theodoric, killed Odoacer and established a new capital city. Belisarius took Rome from, for ten points, what group of eastern Goths?", "answer": "<b> Ostrogoth</b>s (prompt on Goths before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man secured power after hiring North Korea to train the paramilitary Fifth Brigade, which he used to purge political enemies during the Gukurahundi period. This man\u2019s removal of vice president Emerson Mnangagwa led to speculation that he planned to name his unpopular wife Grace as his successor, leading to his removal in a 2017 coup. This man\u2019s reign was marked by an inflation rate that peaked at 100,000 percent in 2008. For ten points, name this longtime ruler of Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Robert<b> Mugabe</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The creation of this regime is remembered by a nationwide sounding of air raid sirens every September 18th. The Lytton Commission was established by the United Nations to investigate the creation of this state, which was founded after a failed dynamite attack on a railway track was used as a pretext for the Kwantung Army to launch an invasion. The Mukden Incident led to the establishment of this state, which installed Pu Yi as emperor. For ten points, name this Japanese puppet state installed in Manchuria.", "answer": "<b> Manchukuo</b> (prompt on (State of) Manchuria before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "While led by Donald Fehr, one of these organizations accused Peter Ueberroth of inciting collusion; that organization of this type was earlier led by Marvin Miller, who worked to nullify the reserve clause in the fight for free agency. An attempt to create one of these organizations at Northwestern University was blocked by the NLRB in 2015, and another one of these organizations was recertified by Roger Goodell after a 2011 lockout. For ten points, name these organizations that represent athletes in collective bargaining.", "answer": "labor<b> union</b>s in sports (accept answers related to professional baseball<b> union</b>s throughout; accept answers related to amateur and/or college football<b> union</b>s<em> after</em> Northwestern is read; accept answers related to professional football<b> union</b>s after \u201cGoodell\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This figure fought Francesco Maria I in the War of Urbino to secure his nephew\u2019s rule over the city. This man received the embassy of the Portuguese king Manuel I, who had previously gifted this man an elephant named Hanno. This man presided over the closing of the Fifth Lateran Council and issued the papal bull<em> Exsurge Domine</em> [ex-oor-gay doh-mee-nay] in condemnation of the author of the 95 Theses. For ten points, name this pope who clashed with Martin Luther.", "answer": "Pope<b> Leo X</b> (accept<b> G</b>iovanni di Lorenzo de\u2019<b> Medici</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This philosopher\u2019s idea that a human being consists merely of its properties and nothing intrinsically substantive is known as his \u201cbundle theory.\u201d This philosopher stirred up controversy by praising polytheism and suggesting it led to monotheistic religions in his (+) </b><em><b>Natural History of Religion</b></em><b>. A law named after this man states that thinkers commit a fallacy when they move from positive to normative statements and is called his (*)</b> \u201cis-ought problem.\u201d For ten points, name this Scottish philosopher who wrote<em> An Enquiry Concerning Human</em> <em>Understanding</em>.", "answer": "David<b> Hume</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Sich autonomous state was created for these people in the Treaty of Pereyaslav, which was signed in the wake of the Khmelnytsky [k\u2019mel-nit-skee] uprising against Polish-</b> <b>Lithuanian control. These people extended their reach to the (+)</b> <b>Terek and Yaik after</b> <b>allying with government forces, but their ranks also included rebellious leaders like Stenka Razin and Yemelyan (*)</b> Pugachev. This group was predominantly centered around the Dnieper and Don rivers. For ten points, name these autonomous horsemen who served as police and military units in 19th century Russia.", "answer": "<b> Cossack</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A turning point in this period was the Battle of Naissus; a cavalry commander at that battle later defeated the Palmyrenes, a breakaway empire that formed during this period. Postumus\u2019s Gallic Empire was also defeated by Aurelian near the end of this period, which</b> <b>began with the (+)</b> <b>Year of the Six Emperors and ended with the rule of Diocletian.</b> <b>Numerous generals took the imperial throne during this period, in which economic (*) </b>breakdown ruined life on the frontier. For ten points, name this century in which the Roman Empire nearly fell completely apart.", "answer": "(Crisis of the)<b> Third Century</b> (AD or CE) Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Women\u2019s Death Battalion supported this man against a 1917 coup by his enemies. This man gained fame reporting on the Lena Goldfields Massacre. This Trudovik names an offensive against Austria-Hungary that is also called the July Offensive. After the (+) Kornilov affair, this man became Commander in Chief; earlier, he replaced Prince Lvov as Prime Minister. A movement against this man called for (*)</b> \u201cpeace, land and bread\u201d and led to the October Revolution. For ten points, name this leader of the Russian Provisional Government who was ousted by the Bolsheviks under Lenin.", "answer": "Alexander<b> Kerensky</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Wei Zheng [\u201cway\u201d zhun] advised this dynasty\u2019s second emperor, Li Shimin [lee sh-ming], also known as Taizong [\u201ctie\u201d-zohn]. The Silla kingdom unified Korea against opposition from this dynasty, whose forces gave up the secret to making (+) paper after being defeated by Muslim troops at the Talas River. This dynasty\u2019s rule was interrupted by the brief Zhou Dynasty, led by Wu Zetian [woo zuh-tehn], China\u2019s only female emperor. (*)</b> An Lushan [ahn loo-shahn] launched a revolt against, for ten points, what dynasty that followed the Sui [swee] and ruled during China\u2019s golden age from the 7th to the 10th century?", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty [or<b> Tang</b> Chao] Page 10", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1986, this country\u2019s leader, Samora Michel, died in a mysterious plane crash. The Rome General Peace Accords ended this country\u2019s civil war. Uria Simango led</b> <b>a Marxist party in this country against the Rhodesian-founded (+)</b> <b>Renamo party.</b> <b>The Frelimo party is the majority party in this country, which is a member of the Commonwealth of Nations despite being a former (*)</b> Portuguese colony. For ten points, name this country that is separated from Madagascar by a namesake channel and governed from Maputo.", "answer": "<b> Mozambique </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}